Guide to the WilliamWordsworth Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Wordsworth collection
1798-1850
GEN MSS 1262
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of letters and writings by William Wordsworth. The autograph letters, signed, are from Wordsworth to his colleagues, friends, and family, along with Wordsworth autographs clipped from letters and documents. One letter contains an autograph addition, signed, by Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Writings in the collection are by Wordsworth, in his hand and that of his sister Dorothy Wordsworth and wife Mary Wordsworth. Also included are groups of page proofs and two published works, Lyrical Ballads with Other Poems, vol. II (London: T. N. Longman and O. Rees, 1800), and Poems in Two Volumes (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, and Orme, 1807), with William and Dorothy Wordsworth's autograph edits for second editions. Other Papers holds one letter from Edward Quillinan to "Miss Tudor" (1850), regarding Wordsworth's death.
Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. For moreinformation see the folder list below.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Biggs andCottle Correspondence Regarding Lyrical Ballads (GEN MSS 1261)
William Wordsworth(1770-1850)
English poet.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of lettersand writings by William Wordsworth. The autograph letters, signed, are fromWordsworth to his colleagues, friends, and family, along with Wordsworthautographs clipped from letters and documents. One letter contains an autographaddition, signed, by Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Writings in the collection are byWordsworth, in his hand and that of his sister Dorothy Wordsworth and wife MaryWordsworth. Also included are corrected page proofs and a volume of poemsWordsworth edited for a second edition. Other Papers holds one letter fromEdward Quillinan to Miss Tudor, regarding Wordsworth's death.
Arrangement
Organizedinto three series: I. Correspondence and Autographs, 1798-1850. II. Writings,1815-1844. III. Other Papers, 1850.
Poets, English -- 19th century; Proofs (printed matter) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Poets -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834; Cookson, William Strickland, 1801-1877; Godwin, William, 1756-1836; Moxon, Edward, 1801-1858; Wordsworth, Dorothy, 1771-1855; Wordsworth, Mary, 1770-1859; Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850; Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850 ( Lyrical ballads); Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850 ( Earlier poems of William Wordsworth)
- Correspondence and Autographs, 1798-1850; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: WilliamWordsworth and Mary Wordsworth.
  Scope and Contents
  Series Icontains autograph letters, signed, from William Wordsworth to his colleagues,friends, and family, along with Wordsworth autographs clipped from letters anddocuments. One letter contains an autograph addition, signed, by Samuel TaylorColeridge. Also present is one autograph letter, signed, by Mary Wordsworth.
  - Wordsworth, William
    - Brown, Mr., 1809 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Custodial History
      Purchased from Metzdorf on theAlbert H. Childs Fund, 1959
    - Calvert, Dr., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Purchased from Goodspeed on theFrancis O. Matthiesen Fund, 1956
    - Cookson, WilliamStrickland, 1826-1838 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Three autograph letters,signed.
      Gift of Paul S. Schoedinger,1942
    - Godwin,William, 1811 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Purchased from Stonehill on the Elizabeth W. Manwaring Fund,1954
    - Johnson,Joseph, 1798 Sep 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Gift of Herman W. Liebert in memory of Andrew Keogh, 1953
      Accompanied by an autograph note, signed and dated March 28,1909, from Violet Wordsworth, explaining the letter.
    - Longman andRees, 1807 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Gift ofChauncey Brewster Tinker (Tinker 668)
      Autograph letter in the hand of Dorothy Wordsworth signed by WilliamWordsworth, also containing an autograph letter, signed, by Samuel TaylorColeridge. Accompanied by a typed letter to Chauncey Brewster Tinker fromBernard Quaritch dated November 10, 1932.
    - Montgomery,James, 1824 Jan 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Gift of Paul S. Schoedinger, 1942
    - Moxon, Edward, 1839 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Gift of Henry C. Hutchins,1952
    - Moxon, Edward, 1843 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Purchased from Stonehill on theChauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1970
      Fragment
    - Murray, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Purchased from Goodspeed on theFrancis O. Matthiesen Fund, 1955
    - Ogle, Harriet, 1842 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Purchased from Stonehill on theChauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1965
    - Perkins, CharlesC., 1849 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Gift of Paul S.Schoedinger, 1942
    - Smith,Southwood, 1849 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Purchased on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund,1976
    - Wilson, Chris, 1850 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Purchased from Stonehill on theAlbert H. Childs Fund, 1961
    - Wordsworth, Christopherand Susan, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Purchased from Stonehill on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker PrizeFund, 1969
    - Unidentifiedrecipient, 1840 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Purchased from W. R. Benjamin on the Francis O. Matthiesen Fund,1962
    - Unidentifiedrecipient, 1842 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Gift of Annie Annie Burr Auchincloss Lewis, 1940
    - Unidentifiedrecipient, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Purchased fromStonehill on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1961
    - Unidentifiedrecipient, 1848 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Autograph written forRev. Benjamin Isaac Haight, 1841 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Gift of E. Clowes Chorley to the Rare Book Room,1941; transferred from the E. Clowes Chorley Collection,1949
    - Autograph notes, circa 1845 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Two autographnotes giving instructions to the printer of his Poems, published by Moxon in1845. The notes were written on and subsequently clipped from the proofs ofthis edition which were sent to the poet for his approval.
      Gift of Herman W. Liebert in memory of Andrew Keogh,1953
    - Autograph mounted on anengraved portrait, 1844 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Removed from: Literary History ofEngland by Margaret Oliphant (London: 1882)[Ib50.ie882]
    - Autographs andhandwriting samples, 1836-1848 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Gift of Wilmarth S. Lewis (Yale 1918),1958
      Autograph signature clipped from letterto Longman and Rees, and two lines of poetry mounted to a card with an image ofRydal Mount
  - Wordsworth, Mary
    - Letter to unidentifiedcorrespondent, 1848 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Writings, 1815-1844; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series two is organized into two subseries: Manuscripts andPage Proofs and Edited Volumes.
  Series IIcontains writings by Wordsworth, in his hand and that of his sister DorothyWordsworth and wife Mary Wordsworth. Also included are corrected page proofsand a volume of poems Wordsworth edited for a second edition.
  - Manuscripts
    - Lines inscribed in thecopy of his poems sent to the Queen for the Royal Library, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Copy in the hand of MaryWordsworth.
      Purchased from John Wilson on theBeinecke No. 1 Fund, 1968
    - "Lo! Where she standsfixed in a saintlike trance", circa 1838 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Purchased from John Wilson on the Beinecke No. 1Fund, 1968
    - Nine sonnets: manuscriptcopies in an unknown hand, after 1838 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Accompanied by a slip of paper bearinginstructions to the printer in Wordsworth's hand and a note intended to bepublished.
    - "A Plea forAuthors", 1838 May (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Autograph drafts, signed, of "A Plea for Authors" (titled here "A Word ortwo from an author") and "'Tis He, whose yester-evening's high disdain" (titledhere "Here follows a 2nd Thrush)
      Purchasedfrom John Wilson on the Beinecke No. 1 Fund, 1968
    - "Poem on a Daisy castingits shadow", 1844 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Two autographpoems on one sheet.
      Purchased from Pickering& Chatto on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1961
    - "Roman Antiquities", undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Autographmanuscript drafts, signed, of "Roman Antiquities" and "A Gravestone on theFloor in the Cloisters of Worcester Cathedral" on one sheet.
      Purchased from John Wilson on the Beinecke No. 1 Fund,1968
    - "The Ruined Cottage" and"Written Upon the Thames Near Richmond", undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Purchased from Driscoll on the Albert H.Childs Fund, 1961
      Two autograph poems in thehand of Robert Southey.
    - "ToEnterprise", circa 1815 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Manuscript draft in the hands of Mary Wordsworth and Sara Hutchinson, withautograph revisions and alterations by William Wordsworth.
    - "The Wishing-GateDestroyed", undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Untitled poem ("Writtenin March 1829 on seeing a Primrose tuft of flowers..."), 1829 Aug 28 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Copied by DorothyWordsworth.
      Purchased from Driscoll on theAlbert H. Childs Fund, 1961
  - Page Proofs and Edited Volumes
    - Lyrical Ballads with Other Poems, vol. II (London:T. N. Longman and O. Rees, 1800), circa 1801 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Formerly owned by John Wordsworth. Purchased on the E. J.and F. W. Beinecke Rare Book Endowment Fund
      Bound volume without title pages and contents, annotated throughout withautograph corrections and revisions by William Wordsworth, Dorothy Wordsworth,and an unidentified person, in preparation for the edition of 1802. Autographof Christopher Wordsworth.
    - Poems, in two volumes (London: Longman, Hurst,Rees, and Orme, 1807), circa 1814 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Ex libris Frederick Locker; ex libris Frank Brewer Bemis; ex libris ChaunceyBrewster Tinker. Bequest of Chauncey Brewster Tinker (Yale1899).
      Bound volume with extensive autographcorrections and textual interpolations by Wordsworth, used in preparing the1815 edition of his poems.
    - Group of page proofs with autograph corrections
      Conditions Governing Access
      Accompanied by preservation photocopy for patronuse.
      Purchased from John Wilson on theAlbert H. Childs Fund and the E. J. and F. W. Beinecke Rare Book EndowmentFund, 1967
      - Poems (1815-1820), circa 1820 (Box 2, Folder 37)
        Sheets of the 1815 edition, correctedby Wordsworth in preparation for the edition of 1820, comprising Volume Ifly-title to page 82 (lacking pages 61-62). and Volume II pages 83-96 and298-356 (lacking 315-316, 353-354, and one leaf between 320 and327).
      - Miscellaneous Poems of William Wordsworth in FourVolumes (1820), circa 1820 (Box 2, Folder 38)
        Sixteen pages of proofs prepared by Wordsworthfor volume III, comprising pages 197-212 (200 and 201 not numbered);corrections and additions in Wordsworth's hand except for page206.
      - Memorials of a Tour on the Continent, 1820 (1822), circa 1822 (Box 2, Folder 39)
        Forty-eight pages of corrected proofs with ten pages of original manuscript,(mostly in Mary Wordsworth's hand) for incorporation in thevolume.
      - Ecclesiastical Sketches (1822) (Box 2, Folder 40)
        Sixty pages of corrected proofscomprising pages 65 to 124, with autograph manuscript of the Advertisement,signed and dated January 24, 1822
    - Ten pages of manuscriptpoems in the hand of Mary Wordsworth, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Purchased from John Wilson on the Albert H. Childs Fund and theE. J. and F. W. Beinecke Rare Book Endowment Fund,1967
- Other Papers, 1850; Series III; 1
  - Autograph letter, signed,from Edward Quillinan to Miss Tudor, regarding Wordsworth's death, 1850 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Purchased from Stonehill onthe Albert H. Childs Fund, 1961